Jacob Bringewatt Curriculum Vitae

jbringew@umd.com • www.jacobbringewatt.com University of Maryland, College Park, Atlantic Building 3303

Summary

I am a PhD candidate in theoretical physics at the University of Maryland, College Park. My research interests span many aspects of quantum information and quantum computing. Current areas of focus include adiabatic quantum computation and quantum annealing, quantum metrology, and quantum algorithms for nuclear theory.

Education

University of Maryland, College Park

College Park, Maryland

PhD in Physics

2018 – 2023 (Expected)

Advisor: Alexey Gorshkov

Bachelor of Science in Physics

2014 - 2018

Cum laude with high honors in physics.

Fellowships, Honors, and Awards

Research Fellowships

KITP Graduate Fellow

2022

Kavli Institute for Theoretical Physics

Computational Science Graduate Fellow (CSGF)

2018-2022

Department of Energy

Lanczos Graduate Fellow

2018-2020

Joint Center for Quantum Information and Computer Science (QuICS),

University of Maryland, College Park

Banneker/Key Scholar

2014-2018

University of Maryland, College Park

Grants

QuICS Seed Grant 2022-2023

Purpose: Funding for an undergraduate researcher during the academic year and a summer student for the 2023 GRAD-MAP Summer Scholars program (see Mentorship below).

Funding Agency: Joint Center for Quantum Information and Computer Science (QuICS)

Amount awarded: \$16.5k

Institute for Robust Quantum Simulation (RQS) Seed Grant

2022-2023

Purpose: Research project on an experiment/theory collaboration to test quantum speed limits using superconducting qubits and explore the possibilities for use speed limits for noise characterization.

Funding Agency: National Science Foundation (NSF)

Amount awarded: \$33k

Contests

Three Minute Thesis (3MT) Contest Winner

2022

College and University Level, University of Maryland, College Park

DOE CSGF Communicate Your Science Contest Winner

2019

Publications

- * denotes equal contribution, † denotes alphabetical order
 - 12. L P García-Pintos, L T Brady, *J Bringewatt*, Y-K Liu. "Lower bounds on quantum annealing times." Preprint. (2022) [arXiv:2210.15687]
 - 11. A Ehrenberg*, *J Bringewatt**, A V Gorshkov. "Minimum entanglement protocols for function estimation." Preprint. (2022) [arXiv:2110.07613]
 - 10. *J Bringewatt*, Z Davoudi. "Parallelization techniques for quantum simulation of fermionic systems." Preprint. (2022) [arXiv:2207.12470]
 - 9. T C Mooney, *J Bringewatt*, N C Warrington, L T Brady. "Lefschetz thimble quantum Monte Carlo for spin systems." Phys. Rev. B 106, 214416 (2022) [arXiv:2110.10699]
 - 8. *J Bringewatt*, L T Brady. "Simultaneous stoquasticity." Phys. Rev. A 105, 062601 (2022) [arXiv:2202.08863]
 - 7. *J Bringewatt*, I Boettcher, P Niroula, P Bienias, A V Gorshkov. "Protocols for estimating multiple functions with quantum sensor networks: geometry and performance." Phys. Rev. Research 3, 033011. (2021) [arXiv:2104.09540]
 - 6. T Qian, *J Bringewatt*, I Boettcher, P Bienias, A V Gorshkov. "Optimal measurement of field properties with quantum sensor networks." Phys. Rev. A (Letter) 103, L030601. (2021) [arXiv:2011.01259]
 - 5. *J Bringewatt*, N Sato, W Melnitchouk, J Qiu, F Steffens, M Constantinou. "Confronting lattice parton distributions with global QCD analysis." Phys. Rev. D. 103, 016003 (2021) [arXiv:2010.00548]
 - 4. *J Bringewatt**, M Jarret*[†]. "Effective gaps are not effective: quasipolynomial classical simulation of obstructed stoquastic Hamiltonians." Phys. Rev. Lett. 125, 170504 (2020) [arXiv:2004.08681]
 - 3. *J Bringewatt*, W Dorland, SP Jordan. "Polynomial time algorithms for estimating spectra of adiabatic Hamiltonians." Phys. Rev. A 100 (3), 032336 (2019) [arXiv:1905.07461]. Editors' Suggestion.
 - 2. *J Bringewatt*, W Dorland, SP Jordan, A Mink. "Diffusion Monte Carlo approach versus adiabatic computation for local Hamiltonians." Phys. Rev. A 97 (2), 022323 (2018) [arXiv:1709.03971]
 - 1. K Pushkin, C Akerlof, D Anbajagane, J Armstrong, M Arthurs, *J Bringewatt*, T Edberg, C Hall, M Lei, R Raymond, M Reh, D Saini, A Sander, J Schaefer, D Seymour, N Swanson, Y Wang, W Lorenzon. "Study of radon reduction in gases for rare event search experiments." Nucl. Instrum. Methods Phys. Res., Sect. A 903, 267-276 (2018) [arXiv:1805.11306]

Patents/Provisional Patents

- 3. T. Qian, J. Bringewatt, I. Boettcher, P. Bienias, A. V. Gorshkov, Systems and Method for Measurement of Field Properties Using Quantum Sensor Networks, U.S. Patent Application 17/978,420, filed Nov 1, 2022. Based on publication [6] above.
- 2. A. Ehrenberg, J. Bringewatt, A. V. Gorshkov, Minimum Entanglement Protocols for Function Estimation, U.S. Provisional Patent Application 63/397546, filed August 12, 2022. Based on publication [11] above.

1. J. Bringewatt, I. Boettcher, P. Niroula, P. Bienias, A. V. Gorshkov, Measurement of Multiple Functions with Quantum Sensor Networks, U.S. Provisional Patent Application 63/363171, filed April 18, 2022. Based on publication [7] above.

Teaching Experience	
Designed and wrote "challenge questions" on quantum information/computing GRAD-MAP Winter Workshop, University of Maryland, College Park	2022
Designed and wrote a self-study packet on quantum computing for high schoolers Girls Talk Math Program, University of Maryland, College Park	202
Math Tutor University of Maryland, College Park	2016-2018
Teaching Assistant for Philosophy of Quantum Mechanics University of Maryland, College Park	2016
Mentorship	
Research	
Othello D. Gomes Undergraduate at University of Maryland (also see GRAD-MAP Winter Worksho)	2022-2023 p below)
Tarushii Goel Undergraduate at MIT	2022
Timothy (Connor) Mooney Undergraduate at George Mason University, now a graduate student at University of Maryland	2021-2022
Akshita Gorti Undergraduate at Cornell University	2021-2022
Timothy Qian High schooler at Montgomery Blair High School, now an undergraduate at MIT, won $5^{\rm th}$ place Regeneron Science Talent Search for work done with me.	2020
Ivy Liang High schooler at Montgomery Blair High School.	2020
GRAD-MAP Winter Workshop GRAD-MAP Winter Workshop is a professional development and research skill-building v ganized via the University of Maryland's Graduate Resources for Advancing Diversity wi Astronomy and Physics program.	
Anisah Khattak Undergraduate at Notre Dame of Maryland University	2023
Othello D. Gomes Undergraduate at Montgomery Community College, now an undergraduate at University of Maryland	2022
Victoria Adebayo Undergraduate at Howard University	2021

Service to the Scientific Community

Peer Review Journals: npj Quantum Information, Quantum Conferences: QIP, TQC			
 Member of UMD Physics Department Graduate Student Colloquium Committee University of Maryland, College Park Volunteer for GRAD-MAP Winter Workshop and Summer Scholars Programs University of Maryland, College Park Co-organizer of Journal Club/Reading Group on Geometry of Quantum States University of Maryland, College Park 	2021–2023 2021–2023 2021–2022		
		Organizer of QuICS-JQI-CMTC Friday Seminar University of Maryland, College Park	2020–2021
		Panelist for Conference for Undergraduate Underrepresented Minorities in Physics (cu2mip) University of Maryland, College Park	2021
Volunteer at University of Maryland Prospective Graduate Student Open Houses University of Maryland, College Park	2019–2021		
Education-related Training and Workshops Seminar Course on Physics Education Research for Teaching Quantum Mechanics University of Maryland, College Park Workshop on Relationships Among Intuition, Reasoning, and Conceptual Understanding in Physics American Association of Physics Teachers	2021		
Seminar Course on Introduction to Physics Education Research University of Maryland, College Park	2020		
Workshop on Science Communication Skype a Scientist organization	2020		
Outreach			
Skype a Scientist Conversations with students (elementary, middle, and high school) on physics.	2020-2022		
Proctor for U.S. Physics Olympiad F=ma Exam	2022		
Writing for Non-scientific Audience "Spherical cows: Using barnyard animals to understand quantum computing." (2019) municate Your Science Essay Contest, published in Deixis Magazine (magazine on of science at DoE national labs)	•		

Presentations

Invited Talks

- 4. "The role of entanglement for function estimation with quantum sensor networks." George Mason University Quantum Computing Seminar. (Feb. 2022)
- 3. "Lefschetz thimble quantum Monte Carlo for spin systems." MIT Computational Research in Boston and Beyond (CRIBB) seminar. (Nov. 2021)
- 2. "Lattice data in the JAM framework." Amherst Center for Fundamental Interactions (ACFI) Workshop on QCD Real-Time Dynamics and Inverse Problems. (Oct. 2020)
- 1. "Confronting lattice parton densities with global QCD analysis." AI for Nuclear Physics Workshop. (Mar. 2020)

Contributed Talks

- 4. "Measuring functions with quantum sensor networks." 23rd Annual SQuInT Workshop. (Oct. 2021)
- 3. "Effective gaps are not effective: quasipolynomial simulation of obstructed stoquastic Hamiltonians." DOE Computational Science Graduate Fellowship Annual Program Review. (July 2021)
- 2. "Optimal measurement of field properties with quantum sensor networks." March Meeting 2021. (Mar. 2021)
- 1. "Confronting lattice parton densities with global QCD analysis." DNP2019. (Oct. 2019)

Seminar Talks

- 14. "The role of entanglement for function estimation with quantum sensor networks." Caltech/ AWS Seminar. (Dec. 2022)
- 13. "Simultaneous stoquasticity." KITP Condensed Matter/Quantum Physics Seminar. (Aug. 2022)
- 12. "The sign problem and quantum advantage." KITP Locals Lunch Seminar. (Aug. 2022)
- 11. "Ultimate limits for function estimation in quantum metrology." Gorshkov Group Meeting. (Jan. 2022)
- 10. "Lefschetz thimble quantum Monte Carlo for spin systems." USC Condensed Matter Seminar. (Nov. 2021)
- 9. "Minimum entanglement protocols for function estimation." QuICS/JQI Friday Quantum Seminar. (Oct. 2021)
- 8. "Fermionic mappings, qubit architectures, and graph coloring." Davoudi Group Meeting. (Aug. 2021)
- 7. "Estimating multiple functions with quantum sensor networks." Gorshkov Group Meeting. (Jan. 2021)
- 6. "Effective gaps are not effective." Gorshkov Group Meeting. (April 2020)
- 5. "Quantum sensor networks and Fisher information." Gorshkov Group Meeting. (Aug. 2019)
- 4. "Confronting lattice parton densities with global QCD analysis." Jefferson Lab Theory Seminar. (July 2019)
- 3. "Diffusion Monte Carlo approach versus adiabatic computation for local Hamiltonians." Gorshkov Group Meeting. (Aug. 2018)
- 2. "Diffusion Monte Carlo approach versus adiabatic computation for local Hamiltonians." University of Maryland Undergraduate Research Showcase. (May 2018)
- 1. "Diffusion Monte Carlo approach versus adiabatic computation for local Hamiltonians." Undergraduate Thesis Defense. (May 2018)

Posters

- 11. "Testing and utilizing quantum speed limits in superconducting systems." Institute for Robust Quantum Simulation NSF Site Visit. (Aug. 2022)
- 10. "Simultaneous stoquasticity." QuICS Stakeholder Day. (Apr. 2022)
- 9. "Lefschetz thimble quantum Monte Carlo for spin systems." QIP2022. (Mar. 2022)
- 8. "Optimal measurement of field properties with quantum sensor networks." QuICS Admitted Students Days. (Apr. and May 2021)
- 7. "Optimal measurement of field properties with quantum sensor networks." QuICS Stakeholder Day. (Mar. 2021)
- 6. "Estimating multiple functions with quantum sensor networks." QuICS 5 Year Anniversary Symposium. (Jan. 2020)
- 5. "Effective gaps are not effective." FARQC Kickoff Meeting. (Nov. 2019)
- 4. "Polynomial time algorithms for estimating spectra of adiabatic Hamiltonians." DOE Computational Science Graduate Fellowship Annual Program Review. (July 2019)
- 3. "Polynomial time algorithms for estimating spectra of adiabatic Hamiltonians." QIP2019. (Jan. 2019)
- 2. "Polynomial time algorithms for estimating spectra of adiabatic Hamiltonians." STAQ Kickoff Meeting. (Nov. 2018)
- 1. "Diffusion Monte Carlo approach versus adiabatic computation for local Hamiltonians." QIP2018. (Jan. 2018)